《夺宝奇兵4：水晶骷髅王国》
嘿 伙计
Hey! Hey, guys!
再快点
Faster!
嘿 你们好啊
Hey, what you got under there?
- 嘿  咱们赛一赛吗？ - 得了吧
- Hey, you want to race?    - Oh, please.
- 来吧!   - 我们走
- Come on!    - Come on, let's go!
来啊
Come on!
- 拜托了 - 来啊  来啊
- Please?    - Come on! Let's go! Come on!
我们走
Come on. Let's go.
开快点  快点
Go faster! Faster!
(原子咖啡馆)
(1957年  美国  内华达州)
先生们 不好意思
Sorry, gentlemen.
因为武器测试  整个地区在24小时内禁止通行
This whole area is closed for weapons testing for the next 24 hours.
包括所有基地的工作人员
That includes all on-base personnel.
长官 下午好
Good afternoon, sir.
这对您也不例外 上校
I'm afraid that goes for you,  too, Colonel, sir.
五角大楼规定…
The Pentagon sent out revised ...
(禁区  无权进入者格杀勿论)
(美国陆军  1B7731  仅供官方使用)
苏联人
Russians.
你以为对付他们很容易
This ain't gonna be easy.
好汉不提当年勇
Not as easy as it used to be.
不过还不是最糟的一次
Well, we've been through worse.
是吗？那最糟的是哪次？
Yeah? When?
昆茨堡那次  当时敌人比我们多一倍
Flensburg. There was twice as many.
- 那时我们还年轻  - 我仍然很年轻
- We were younger.    - I still am young!
那次我们手上有枪
We had guns.
把手放下  真丢人
Put your hands down, will you? You're embarrassing us.
我们准能脱险  我赌五百块
Bet you 500 bucks we can get out of this.
还是赌一百吧
Let's call it 100.
知道这是哪儿吗？
You recognize building, yes?
放下死者
Drop dead.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我是说去死吧  同志
I meant drop dead, comrade.
按住他
住手!
- 在哪儿找到他们的？ - 墨西哥
- Where was he found?    - In Mexico.
他们在夜里挖宝  找这些东西
They were digging in the dirt, looking for this stuff.
你不是本地人  是不是？
You're not from around here, are you?
琼斯博士  你不会想知道我是哪里人的
Where is it you would imagine I am from, Dr. Jones?
根据你那副不可一世的样子
Well, the way you're sinking your  teeth into those wubble-u's,
我猜你是来自乌克兰东部
I should think maybe Eastern Ukraine.
很高的评价
Highest marks.
我是艾琳娜·史波可博士
Colonel Dr. Irina Spalko.
我获得过列宁勋章 三次
Three times I have received Order of Lenin.
以及英雄的社会主义劳动者奖章
Also medal as Hero of Socialist Labor.
为什么？
And why?
因为我无所不知  我知人所未知
Because I know things. I know them before anyone else.
而且若我不知  我会查出来
And what I do not know, I find out.
而我现在想知道的  就在这儿
Now, what I need to know now is in here.
- 琼斯博士  你很难感知嘛  - 好痛呀
- You are a hard man to read, Dr. Jones.    - Ouch.
那我们只好按老规矩办事了
So, we will do this, what is  expression, old-fashioned way.
那样你就会帮我们找到想要的东西
You will tell us. You will help us find what we seek.
把门打开
这间仓库就是你们政府存放所有秘密的地方吗？
This warehouse is where you  and your government have hidden all of your secrets, yes?
这是间军用仓库 我此前从没来过
This is a military warehouse. I've never been here before in my life.
我们要找的东西装在长方形盒子内
Object we seek, rectangular storage container,
盒子长2米 宽0.5米 厚66厘米
dimensions 2 meters by 0.5 meter by 66 centimeters.
里面装的是具遗骸
Contents of box, mummified remains.
你难道不知此事？
This is no doubt familiar to you.
你凭什么认为我会知道？
What makes you think I've got any idea what box you're talking about?
因为在十年前...
Because 10 years ago ...
是你带领小组找到它的
you were part of the team that examined it.
听着…
Look ...
我知道你说的是什么了…
Even if I knew  what you were talking about ...
你要帮我们找到它
You will help us find it.
指南针 我需要个指南针
Compass. I need a compass.
就是用来指北 南 东...
You know, north, south, east West.
还有西
没指南针吗？
No compass?
把你的子弹给我
I need your bullets.
哈哈 他要我把枪给他
那个盒子有极高的磁性
The contents of that box are highly magnetized.
给我火药
I need gunpowder.
你想不想要我帮你？
You want my help or not?
别和我耍花招  琼斯博士  你到底在搞什么鬼？
Don't toy with me, Dr. Jones. What is the point of all this?
如果那盒子依然具有磁性
If it's still magnetic,
这火药中的铁屑会指引方向的
the metal in this gunpowder should point the way.
这边走
弹壳  给我些散弹
Shells. Give me some shotgun shells.
钳子
Pliers.
找到了
同志们 找到了
过来几个人把它抬出来
在这儿  小心
用力  小心  稳住  稳住
(新墨西哥州 罗斯威尔  1947年  编号RSW001)
给我把刀
刀 给您
终于找到了
把枪都放下! 不然史波可博士就死定了
Drop the guns, or Colonel Dr. Spalko is dead.
麦克 为什么？
Why, Mac?
琼斯  要我怎么说呢
Well, what can I say, Jonesey?
我信奉资本主义  而他们出价不低
I'm a capitalist, and they pay.
这么多年来  我们同甘共苦
After all those years we spent spying on the Reds?
我还以为我们是朋友呢
I thought we were friends, Mac.
如果不是我不幸被他们抓住的话
I've had a run of bad luck with the cards lately, mate.
可怕  太他妈可怕了
Awful. Bloody awful.
我不能再两手空空地回家了
I can't go home empty-handed again.
琼斯博士  想好遗言了吗？
No defiant last words, Dr. Jones?
我热爱考古
I like Ike.
放下枪
Put down gun.
放下就放下
You got it, pal.
抓住他!
该死  就差一点
Damn, I thought that was closer.
来啊  来啊
Come on. Come on.
他不能活着离开这儿  派人去截住他
别傻了  鲍里斯  你不了解情况
Don't get clever, Boris. You don't know him.
不要  不要
Know him. Know him.
你没搞清楚  你不了解他
You don't know him! You don't know him!
你不了解他  你不了解他...
You don't know him!  You don't know ...
你干得不错
You did well.
那玩意儿酷极了!
喂  有人在家吗？
Hello? Hello?
喂
Hello!
嘿  我过敲门了  你们…
Hey. I knocked.  You guys got a ...
等一下
Wait a minute.
情况不妙
Oh, that can't be good.
所有人注意  一分钟内撤离
All personnel, it is now one minute to zero time.
戴好墨镜  向相反方向撤离
Put on goggles or turn away.
在第一次闪光后十秒内  不要摘掉墨镜回头看
Do not remove goggles or face burst until 10 seconds after first light.
大事不妙了
That can't be good at all.
撤退 我们快走!
等等 等一下
Wait! Wait!  Wait, wait, wait! Wait!
好  他妈的  不等我
Sure! Great! Don't wait for me!
15秒倒计时
Minus 15 seconds.
10秒倒计时
Minus 10 seconds.
九 八 七 六
Niner, eight, seven, six,
五 四
fiver, four,
三 二 一 发射
three, two, one, zero.
我真的不知道麦克是间谍
I had no reason to believe that Mac was a spy.
我为战略情报局工作时 他为军情六处工作
He was Ml6 when I was in OSS.
在欧洲和太平洋地区  我们合作过二三十次了
We did 20, 30 missions together in Europe and the Pacific.
别在我们面前显摆你的功绩了  琼斯上校
Don't wave your war record in our face, Colonel Jones.
我们都曾为国效力
We all served.
你什么意思？你们站在那一边的？
No kidding?  What side were you on?
我想你已经认识到局势的严重性了
I don't think you recognize the gravity of your situation.
你刚刚协助克格勃特务侵入了
You aided and abetted KGB agents who broke into a top-secret  military installation ...
我们国家中部的秘密军事基地
in the middle of the United States of America, my country.
被窃的那个钢盒里是什么东西？
What was in the steel box they took?
这个应该你告诉我们  你以前见过的
You tell us. You've seen it before.
你是指47年的那次任务
You mean that Air Force fiasco in '47.
我被塞进一辆密不透风的车
I was tossed into a bus with blacked-out windows ...
还不许和同车的20人说话
and 20 people I wasn't allowed to speak to.
半夜出发去执行紧急挖掘任务
Hauled out in the middle of the  night in the middle of nowhere ...
不知道去哪儿  而又能看到什么？
on some urgent recovery project and shown what?
毫无遮掩的具有强磁性的碎片  还有不同寻常的遗迹
Pieces of wreckage and an intensely magnetic shroud covering mutilated remains?
我们谁都不知道那是什么
None of us was ever given the full picture.
并被威胁如果和任何人说起 就会被处以叛国罪
And we were threatened with treason if we ever talked about it.
所以应该是你们告诉我  那盒子里到底装的是什么？
So, you tell me,  what was in the box?
印第  谢天谢地
Indy, thank God.
你知道躲在冰箱里有多危险吗？
Don't you know it's dangerous to climb into a refrigerator?
那些东西可能正是陷阱呢
Those things can be deathtraps!
见到你真好  鲍勃
Good to see you, too, Bob.
放松  伙计们  我来和琼斯博士谈
Relax, boys.  I can vouch for Dr. Jones.
到底发生什么事了？
What the hell is going on?
克格勃跑到美国本土来了  那女人是谁？
KGB on American soil? Who is that woman?
描述一下
Describe her.
又高又瘦  三十多岁  还带着把破剑
Tall, thin, mid-30s, carried a sword of some kind, a rapier, I think.
没错  就是她
Yeah, that's her.
你确定她在此地？
You sure she's here?
来了又走了  她是谁？
Here and gone. Who is she?
艾琳娜·史波可  她是斯大林的干女儿
Irina Spalko, she was Stalin's fair-haired girl.
也是著名科学家  如果通灵术也算是科学的话
His favorite scientist, if you  can call psychic research science.
罗斯将军…
General Ross ...
她率领队伍转战世界各地
She's leading teams from the  Kremlin all over the world.
四处搜集她认为有军事价值的古物
Scooping up artifacts she thinks might have paranormal military applications.
- 罗斯将军  - 闭嘴  保罗
- General Ross!    - Back off, Paul.
不是每个人都是共产党间谍   印第更不会是
Not everyone in the Army's a Commie and certainly not Indy.
除了没被核弹炸死外  对我还有什么指控吗？
What exactly am I being accused of, besides surviving a nuclear blast?
目前还没有指控
Nothing yet.
但老实说  鉴于你同乔治·麦克希尔的关系
But frankly your association with George McHale ...
使你在二战时的行为有些可疑
makes all your activities suspicious, including those during the war.
你们疯了吗？
Are you nuts?
你们知道这帮杂种还要多少这样的金属吗？
Do you have any idea how many medals this son of a bitch won?
肯定不少
A great many, I'm sure.
但他们受之有愧
But does he deserve them?
琼斯博士  你现在对政府很重要
Dr. Jones, let's just say for now that you are of interest to the Bureau.
至关重要
Of great interest.
同样的东西
Grooved Ware in the beginning of modern drainage practices,
在苏格兰斯卡拉布雷遗址也被发现
which we also see in Skara Brae on the west coast of Scotland.
该遗址可以追溯到公元前3100年
Skara Brae dates from 3100 B.C.
六百年来 它一直被占领着
and was continuously occupied for 600 years ...
直至公元前2500年被遗弃
until it was apparently abandoned in 2500 B.C.
现在还没有令人信服的证据
There's no clear evidence as to why its occupants ...
表明为何占领者决定放弃一个完美的生存环境
decided to abandon a perfectly  healthy environment. Yes?
- 能打扰一下吗  教授？ - 好吧
- May I have a moment, Professor?    - Yes.
打开书  复习第四章
Open up Michaelson.  Review Chapter 4.
一会儿我回来后  我们讨论迁徙和"出埃及"的不同
When I come back we'll discuss the difference between migration and exodus.
什么？
What?
我不知道  学校董事会不停施压
You have no idea the pressure coming from the Board of Regents.
联邦调查局今早来过
The FBI showed up this morning,
搜遍了你的办公室  查抄了所有文件
ransacked your office, searched all your files!
这可是在学校啊  你怎么不阻止他们？
You're the dean of the college. Why didn't you stop them?
他们没这个权利
They have no right.
完全有这个权利  他们是群畜生
They had every right! They weren't vandals.
是带着搜查令的特务
They were federal agents with search warrants!
学校不会冒险卷入此类麻烦
The university isn't gonna get itself embroiled in that kind of controversy,
像你这种情况更不行
not in this charged climate.
你这就是要开除我了
So you're firing me.
只是让你暂时离职  没别的
A leave of absence is all. An indefinite leave of absence.
- 就是开除  - 此间...
- You are firing me.    - During which ...
他们还会付你全额的工资…
they've agreed to continue to pay your full salary for a period ...
我才不要他们的钱
I don't want their money!
求求你别犯傻了
Please don't be foolish.
你不知道我费了多大劲才给你争取到的
You don't know what I had to go  through to get that for you.
你还费劲儿？你又能费什么劲  查理？
You went through? What exactly did you have to go through, Charlie?
亨利…
Henry ...
我辞职了
I resigned.
你准备去哪儿？
Where will you go?
先去纽约  明早去伦敦  重新开始
Train to New York, overnight to London, for starts.
为什么我不去莱比锡大学呢？他们的校长欠我人情
I might end up teaching in Leipzig. Heinrich owes me a favor.
等我定居下来 我就给你写信
I'll wire you when I get settled.
你再把剩下的东西给我寄过去
You can send on the rest of my things.
那时东西早被搜光了  都不用寄了
I suppose there's nothing to keep you here.
这个国家已经面目全非了
I barely recognize  this country anymore.
政府总是怀疑我们是共产党
The government's got us seeing Communists in our soup.
当疯狂战胜科学时  换换工作也不错
When the hysteria reaches academia, I guess it's time to call it a career.
迪尔丽德怎么受得了呢？
How did Deirdre take the news?
妻子通常都是怎么接受的呢？
How does any wife take such things?
看着丈夫的脸  混杂着自豪与惊恐
The look on her face was  a combination of pride and panic.
我不该怀疑你的  我的朋友
I never should've doubted you, my friend.
没关系  这几天你怀疑朋友也可以理解
No, you have reason to question your friends these days.
过了好几年了  查理
Brutal couple of years, huh, Charlie?
先是爸爸  然后是马库斯
First Dad, then Marcus.
我们到年纪啦  生活不再给予而是开始带走我们的挚爱
We seem to have reached the age where life stops giving us things and starts taking them away.
再喝半杯
Just another half glass.
嘿
Hey!
嘿  老头
Hey, old man!
你好 教授 喂 你是琼斯博士吗？
Professor, hello! Hey! Are you Dr. Jones?
火车快出站了  孩子
You're running out of platform, kid.
你是奥克斯利教授的朋友吗？
Are you a friend of Dr. Oxley's?
- 是那个考古学家哈洛德·奥克斯利吗？- 没错
- Harold Oxley? The archeologist?    - Yeah.
他怎么了？
What about him?
他有生命危险
They're going to kill him.
我有20年没同他说话了
I haven't talked to Harold Oxley in 20 years.
他是个出色的学者
He's a brilliant guy.
是那种能把你说得昏昏欲睡的人
He could put you to sleep just by talking.
没错  很多孩子听他说话都会睡着
Yeah. Yeah. When I was a kid, that's how I did get to sleep.
他的声音比牛奶还催眠
Oxley's voice was better than a glass of warm milk, you know.
我叫马特·威廉姆斯
The name's Mutt, Mutt Williams.
马特？怎么取这个名字？
Mutt? What kind of name is that?
混蛋  你找揍吗？
It's the one I picked. You got a problem with it?
放松点儿  你和奥力克斯博士有什么关系？
Take it easy. What was your relationship to Oxley?
我爹死于二战  他帮助我妈抚养我
My dad died in the war. Ox kind of helped my mom raise me.
你的意思是有人要取他性命？
You were saying somebody's going to kill him?
6个月前  我妈收到奥克斯的来信
Six months ago, my mom gets a letter from the Ox.
说他在秘鲁
He's down in Peru.
发现了什么骷髅头  水晶骷髅头骨
Found some type of skull, a crystal skull.
就是那个叫米切尔-哈提基思什么的人？
Like the one that guy Mitchell-Hodgkiss? Hedgkiss?
- 就是他发现的那个  - 外套不错
- The one he found.    - Nice jacket.
大学里只有奥克斯和我研究水晶骷髅头骨
The Ox and I were obsessed with the Mitchell-Hedges skull in college.
你怎么知道这个？
How do you know about it?
你说呢？他成天只说这个
Are you kidding?  It's all he talked about.
一回家就说
He'd talk about that thing till the cows come home.
那是个神秘雕像吗？
What's it? It's like an idol?
做工精美  在美洲中部被发现
Deity carving. Mesoamerican.
世界上有很多水晶骷髅头
There are a number of crystal skulls in the world.
我在大英博物馆见过一个
I saw one in the British Museum.
很有趣的水晶赝品  没什么
Interesting craftsmanship, but that's about it.
好了  我们等会再谈那个  奥克斯说这次他找到真的了
All right, well, laugh if you want. Oxley said he found it this time.
而且要将其还于埃克托
He said this was real and he was off to a place called Akator with it.
- 埃克托？你确定他是这么说的吗？ - 我确定
- Akator? He said that? You're sure? - Yeah.
跟你刚说的一样  你说埃克托  那是什么东西？
That's what he said. He said Akator. What is it?
是亚马孙河流域传说中的失落之城
It's a mythical lost city  in the Amazon.
西班牙探险者称之为"黄金国"
Conquistadors called it El Dorado.
据说是神选的布伽族人在七千年前
Supposedly, the Ugha tribe were chosen by the gods 7,000 years ago ...
以实心金砖建造的巨大的城市
to build a giant city  out of solid gold.
其建筑的工艺水平
It had aqueducts and paved roads ...
建造技术在之后五千年内再未出现过
and technology that wouldn't  be seen again for 5,000 years.
弗朗西斯科·尤里奥纳于1546年到亚马逊探索该城未果而失踪
Francisco de Orellana disappeared into the Amazon looking for it in 1546.
我也曾试图寻找它  但险些丧命
I almost died of typhus looking for it myself.
我不相信它存在
I don't think it exists.
为什么奥克斯要把骷髅头带到那去？
Why would Ox want to take the skull there?
据传说 骷髅头于15或16世纪时被人从埃克托窃走
The legend says that a crystal  skull was stolen from Akator in the 15th or 16th century,
无论谁 若能将它归还城市神庙
and that whoever returns  the skull to the city temple ...
作为报答将会掌控某种力量
will be given control over its power.
力量？关系到了某种力量 是什么样的力量？
Power. Right. So there's some kind of power. What's the power?
我不知道  孩子  只是个传说
I don't know, kid.  It's just a story.
不
No.
我妈收到奥克斯的信之后
From his letter, my mom thought the Ox was off his rocker. You know, smog in the noggin,
她就去找他  而他已经被绑架了
so she goes down there to find him, only he'd already been kidnapped.
现在他们也抓住了她
Now they've got her, too.
奥克斯说他们在某个地方
Now, Ox said he hid that skull someplace,
我妈要是不能提供有用的信息  他们两人都会没命的
and if my mom doesn't come up with it, they're gonna kill them both.
她说你能帮我
Now, she said you'd help me.
我？令堂的名字是？
Me? What's your mom's name again?
玛丽安·威廉姆斯  你还记得她吗？
Mary. Mary Williams. You remember her?
我认识许多叫玛丽安的人  孩子
There were a lot of Marys, kid.
住口  你说的可是我老妈
Shut up! That's my mother you're talking about!
是我母亲  好吗？
All right? That's my mother.
你也不必拍桌子瞪眼的  来让自己显得像个硬汉吧
You don't have to get sore all the  time just to prove how tough you are.
坐下  请坐下吧
Sit down. Please. Sit down.
她说你能找到骷髅头
She said if anybody could find  the skull, it's you.
你是个…盗墓贼什么的吧
Like you're some type of ... Like a grave robber or something.
我是考古学的终身教授
I'm a tenured professor of archeology.
哦  你是老师  那就更能帮我了
Oh, you're a teacher. Well, that's gonna be a big help.
不管怎样  我妈两周前从南美打电话给我
Anyway, she called me two weeks ago from South America.
说她逃出来了  他们在追她
Said she'd escaped, but they were after her.
她有封奥克斯转给你的信
She said she'd just gotten a letter from the Ox ...
让我转交给你
and mailed it to me so I could give it to you.
电话就断了  我拆开看了
Then the line went dead.  I opened it.
但看不懂  乱码
I mean, the thing's pointless,  though. It's just gibberish.
都不是用英文写的
It's not even English lettering.
是吧？
See?
看到那两个盯梢的了吧？ 在桌旁的那两个
See those two bricks over there, at the counter?
他们可不是来喝奶昔的
I don't think they're here for the milkshakes.
他们是谁？
Who are they?
不知道  可能是调查局的人
Don't know. Maybe FBI.
别轻举妄动  琼斯博士
Come quietly, Dr. Jones.
这说明他们是克格勃
Make that KGB.
- 把信交出来  - 信？什么信？
- And bring letter with you.    - Letter? What letter?
就是威廉姆斯先生刚给你的
Letter Mr. Williams just give you.
我？我看起来像个邮递员吗？
Me? Do I look like a mailman?
我们不会再说一次了  现在就跟我们走 不然…
We don't ask again. Come now or we'll ...
不然怎样
Or what?
不错的尝试 孩子  但我看你是带了把刀去参加枪战
Nice try, kid, but I think  you just brought a knife to a gunfight.
马上出去
Outside now.
- 揍这小子  - 揍谁？
- Hit this guy.    - Who?
正要结帐出去这个
Joe College. Hit him hard.
- 你好啊  - 什么？
- Here, hold this.    - What?
那是我男朋友
That's my boyfriend!
揍这帮飚车党
Get that greaser!
不是你妈逃出来了
Your mom didn't escape.
是他们放了她  好让她把信寄给你
They let her go, so she could mail the letter ...
然后让你把信给我  我就可以破译它
and you could bring it to me and I could translate it!
快 他们要跑了
上车
Get on, gramps!
快! 快! 快! 快!
Go, go, go, go, go!
抓住他  抓住他
他拐弯了  跟上
该死
他们在那儿 跟上
宁死不红 宁死不红
Better dead than Red! Better dead than Red!
真是疯了 有人会受伤的
This is crazy! Somebody's going to get hurt!
(马库斯·布鲁迪)
在那儿  跟上他们
向左拐
Left! Go left! Left!
让开  让开
Move, move! Move!
闪开 闪开 闪开
Split, split! Split, split!
- 我们开得太快了  - 只有你觉得快
- You're going too fast.    - That's a matter of opinion!
- 打扰一下  琼斯博士  - 什么事？
- Excuse me, Dr. Jones.    - Yes?
关于哈格罗伍的文化图腾  我有个问题
I just had a question on Hargrove's normative culture model.
还是算了吧
Forget Hargrove.
去查阅范戈登·蔡尔德的著作
Read Vere Gordon Childe on diffusionism.
他在这个领域钻研了一辈子
He spent most of his life  in the field.
若想成为个优秀的考古学家
If you want to be  a good archeologist,
就得走出图书馆
you got to get out of the library!
那是谁？
Who is that?
弗朗西斯科·迪·尤里奥纳
Francisco de Orellana, the conquistador.
我曾说过他在寻找骷髅头时失踪了
Remember, the guy who got lost looking for the skull.
正如我所猜测
And just as I thought.
"科尤玛"
Koihoma.
那是什么？
What's that?
是种失传的拉丁美洲语言  索拉比克语的语源
It's an extinct Latin American language. Pre-Columbian syllabic base.
看 虽然字体不同  但线条差不多  绝对是科尤玛语
See. Diagonal stresses on the  ideograms. Definitely Koihoma.
- 你会说这种语言吗？ - 没人会说
- You speak it?    - Nobody speaks it.
3千年来  听到这种语言的人都不多
It hasn't been heard aloud in 3,000 years.
也许我能看懂一点  不过得先复习一下玛雅语
I might be able to read a bit though if I walk it through Mayan first.
对于一个老家伙来说  你打架一点都不逊
You know, for an old man, you ain't bad in a fight.
多谢夸奖
Thanks a lot.
你有八十岁了吧？
What are you, like, 80?
这是个谜语
It's a riddle.
很符合奥克斯的风格  用消亡了的语言写成谜语
Leave it to Ox to write a riddle in a dead language.
"跟随地球上那条只有上帝才能看到的线"
"Follow the lines in the earth only gods can read ...
"指引你找到有活死人守护着的尤里奥纳的摇篮"
"which lead to Orellana's cradle guarded by the living dead."
- 他说的是纳兹卡线  - 什么东西？
- He's talking about the Nazca Lines.    - What are those?
等一下
Hold on here.
巨大而古老的地表图画雕刻在秘鲁沙漠的地面上
Geoglyphs. Giant ancient drawings carved into the desert floor in Peru.
在地上看是看不出什么名堂的
From the ground, they don't look like anything.
但是从空中 只有上帝可懂
But from the sky, only the gods can read them,
因为只有上帝高高在上
because only gods live up there.
奥克斯利想告诉我们  骷髅就在秘鲁的纳兹卡
Oxley's telling us the skull is in Nazca, Peru.
终于知道有人看见过他了
Finally. They saw him.
奥克斯几个月前来过  像个疯子似的
Ox wandered into town a couple of  months ago, raving like a madman.
警察把他关进修道院  走这边
Police locked him up  in the sanitarium. It's this way.
他们说的西班牙语  我一个字都不懂  那到底是什么？
I took Spanish and I didn't understand a word of that. What was it?
"卡图瓦"  当地土话
Quechua, local Incan dialect.
- 你怎么学会的？ - 说来话长
- Where'd you learn that one?    - Long story.
我有的是时间
I got time.
我和"庞驰·维拉"待过  他的手下会这种话
I rode with Pancho Villa. A couple of his guys spoke it.
扯谈!
Bullshit!
- 你问我的  - 庞驰·维拉!
- You asked.    - Pancho Villa?
- 实际上  我是被绑架去的  - 被庞驰·维拉的人？
- Technically, I was kidnapped.    - By Pancho Villa?
那是在与维克多瑞亚·胡塔的交战中
It was the fight against Victoriano Huerta.
- 那时你多大？ - 那时我就你这么大
- How old were you?    - About your age.
你父母肯定急疯了吧？
Your parents must've had a cow, huh?
当时和家人的关系有点紧张
It worked out. Things were a little tense at home.
我和老妈相处得也不是很融洽
Yeah, me and my mom aren't on the best of terms, either.
孩子  要知道你只会有一个妈  而且也不能陪你一生
Treat her right, kid. You only get  one and sometimes not for that long.
那可不是我的错  是她的错
It's not my fault. It's hers.
她勃然大怒  因为我退学了
She just got P.O.'ed because I quit school.
她以为我是个一事无成的家伙
She thinks I'm some  kind of goof or something.
- 你退学了？ - 没错  还不只一次呢
- You quit school?    - Oh, yeah. Sure. Tons of them.
我在几所有名的预科学校读过书 学辩论  国际象棋  剑术
Fancy prep schools that teach you how to debate and chess and fencing.
我才不相信什么学位呢  那只是浪费时间而已
I'm great with the blade. I just think it's a waste of time.
- 你从没读完  - 对
- You never finished.    - No.
只学了一些无用的技能罢了
Just a bunch of useless skills. Wrong books.
可我喜欢阅读  我过去整天都看书
'Cause I love reading. Me and Ox used to read all the time.
现在我能证明自己了  相信吗
But now I can pick them myself. You get me?
- 你从哪儿来的钱？ - 参加摩托车赛
- What do you do for money?    - Fix motorcycles.
你一辈子都准备干这个吗？
Gonna do that for the rest of your life?
也许我会的  你觉得不好吗？
Maybe I will, Teach. You got a problem with that?
不  只要是你喜欢做的事
No. Not if that's  what you love doing.
就别管别人怎么说
Don't let anybody tell you different.
就是这里了
This is it. Sister.
她说奥克斯原来就在儿  现在不知去哪儿了
She says Ox isn't here. She doesn't know where he is.
有些人来抓走了他   一些拿着枪的人
Some men came and took him away, men with guns.
她说他着魔了  神经错乱
She says he was obsessed, deranged.
把监牢的墙上画满图片
Drew pictures all over the walls of his cell.
奥克斯信中的谜语一点道理都没有
This riddle in Oxley's letter doesn't make any sense.
"跟随只有上帝才能看见的线"
"Follow the lines that only the gods can read "
"它会引领你到尤里奥纳的摇篮"
" that lead to Orellana's cradle. "
摇篮  他的出生地
Cradle, cradle, birth.
尤里奥纳不是生于秘鲁  而是在西班牙
Orellana wasn't born in Peru. He was born in Spain.
他是探险者  来这儿是为了黄金
He was a conquistador. He came here for the gold.
他后来怎么了？
What happened to him?
他和其它六名队员  活不见人死不见尸
He disappeared along with six others. Their bodies were never found.
奥克斯疯了
He must have lost his mind.
到底发生了什么？奥克斯到底怎么了？
Ox, man, what happened? What happened?
这个不是米切尔·哈提斯基的骷髅头
This is not the Mitchell-Hedges skull.
看  后脑线条较长
Look at the elongated cranium.
用不同的语言一遍遍写着相同的话
And the same word in different languages, over and over again.
归还   回归
回返
Return.
返回哪里？
Return where?
或者归还什么东西
Or return what?
你的意思是骷髅头？
You mean the skull?
萦绕在他脑海中的事物
Seems to have been on his mind.
很可能是那东西该归还给谁
Where was he supposed to return it to?
- 扫干净  - 好的
- Sweep.    - Yeah.
奥克斯说的不是尤里奥纳的出生地
Ox didn't mean Orellana's birthplace.
"摇篮"在玛雅语中还有另一个意思
Cradle has another meaning in Mayan.
直译为安息地  和坟墓是一个意思
Literally, it means "resting place," as in final resting place.
奥克斯是说  尤里奥纳的墓地
Ox meant Orellana's grave.
就在这儿了  他就埋葬于此处
This drawing scratched into the floor is the cemetery where he's buried.
你说过尤里奥纳蒸发了  没人找到过他的坟墓
You said Orellana vanished and nobody ever found his grave.
看起来老奥克斯利找到了
Well, it looks like Harold Oxley did.
盗墓贼会大吃一惊的
"Grave robbers will be shot."
好在我们不是盗墓贼
Good thing we're not grave robbers.
- 我们要找什么？ - 还不知道呢
- What are we looking for?    - I don't know yet.
也许是这众多墓穴中的一个
Maybe an antechamber off one of these barrows.
我刚才好像看见什么了
I think I just saw something!
你真是疑神疑鬼啊
Oh, you're jumping at shadows.
从这儿下去
This way down.
- 从这儿上来  - 好吧
- This way up.    - Yeah.
镖上有毒!
Those darts are poison!
待着别动
Stay there.
你是老师？
You're a teacher?
兼职的
Part-time.
死路一条
Dead end.
可能
Maybe.
你在干嘛？放下那东西
What are you doing? Put that thing away.
给我照亮点
Give me some light over here.
到这儿来
Bring it over here.
什么东西？
It's just a thing.
你胆子好小  一惊一乍的
Dance on your own dime, will you?
我刚才被蝎子叮了一下  不会没命吧
One of the scorpions just stung me! Am I gonna die?
- 多大一只？ - 巨大
- How big?    - Huge!
- 很好  - 这还好？
- Good.    - Good?
说到蝎子  越大毒性越小
When it comes to scorpions, the bigger the better.
要是小蝎子咬了你  就一定要告诉我
A small one bites you, don't keep it to yourself.
骷髅  看这些骷髅  老兄
Their skulls.  Look at their skulls, man.
和牢房墙上画的如出一辙  说明离得不远了
Like the drawings in Oxley's cell. Means we're getting closer.
真疯狂  头骨怎么会变成这形状
That's crazy. Why is it like that?
当地土人用布条缠绑婴儿的头部  使颅骨变形
Nazca Indians used to bind their infants' heads with rope
成了现在这模样
to elongate the skull like that.
- 为什么？ - 敬奉诸神
- Why?    - Honor the gods.
不  不  神灵的脑袋长得可不像这样
No, no.  God's head is not like that, man.
谁又知道神长啥样呢
Depends on who your god is.
你不知道去哪  还走这么快
You're going nowhere fast.
教授  这儿真的是死路一条啊
Professor, this really is a dead end. Look.
嘿
Hey!
过来吧  天才 把背包给我
Come on, genius.  Bring the backpack.
- 太难以置信了  - 真的假的啊
- This is incredible.    - Unreal.
什么都别乱动
Don't touch anything.
脚印  有人来过这里
Footprints. Somebody's been here.
不久之前
Recently.
有两种脚印
Two sets of prints.
看看大小  也许同一个人来了两回
Same size, could have been the same person twice.
说的不错
Not bad, kid.
一 二
One. Two.
三 四 五 六
Three. Four. Five. Six.
七
Seven.
尤里奥纳和他的人看来根本就没到达雨林
Orellana and his men might've made it out of the jungle after all.
照亮一点
Give me some light.
你随身带着刀 对吧？
You don't have a knife, do you?
看起来像昨天才死的人
Looks like he just died yesterday.
裹尸布让他们保存完好
It's the wrappings.  They preserved him.
发生什么事了？
What just happened?
被包裹了500年  接触空气可不行
He's been wrapped up for 500 years. Air doesn't agree with him.
谢谢
Thanks.
我想借这把刀去使使已经好多年了
I don't want to keep borrowing yours all the time.
- 这没什么  - 还是还给他吧
- That's fine.    - I was going to put it back.
这具尸骸也被人打开了吗？
Is this one open already?
是他
It's him.
是尤里奥纳本人
It's Orellana himself.
散发着金子般光芒的男人  因传说中的黄金而失去踪影
They called him The Gilded Man. His lust for gold was legendary.
真不幸啊
It's odd.
有人来了又走了
Somebody's been here and gone.
但黄金  所有器物还在
But they left all this gold and all the artifacts.
他们要找的是什么？
What were they looking for?
- 拿着  - 不 不
- Hold this.    - No. No.
太不可思议了
Unbelievable.
鬼斧神工  浑然天成
No tool marks.
由一块材料雕刻而成
A single piece of seamless quartz.
把大脑分成两个半球
Cut across the grain.
即使今日的科技也无法做到这点
It's not possible, even with today's technology, it would shatter.
水晶没有磁性
Crystal's not magnetic.
这是金子做的
Neither is gold.
这是什么东西？
What is this thing?
也许当地土人认为这就是他们的神
Maybe the Nazca Indians thought this was their god.
- 你认为这个就是从…  - 埃克托城
- You think this is the one from ...    - From Akator.
也许这些西班牙佬发现了骷髅头和其它的珍宝
Maybe the Spaniards found this skull along with all this other loot.
便朝海边的舰队走去
They were headed for their ships along the shore.
也许印第安人发现并杀了他们
Maybe the Indians  caught up with them,
或者西班牙人起了内讧
or they got to squabbling amongst themselves ...
相互残杀
over their prize,  kill each other off.
印第安人将他们包裹安葬
The Indians wrap them up and bury them.
几百年后  奥克斯利来到此处找到骷髅
A couple of hundred years later, Oxley shows up here, finds the skull.
将其带走 也许带到了埃克托
Takes it away, maybe to Akator.
他随即又返回了此地
But then he returns it here.
返回
Return.
"返回" 和监牢墙上的字是一个意思
Return, like he wrote on the walls of his cell.
他将此物归还  为什么？
He put it back  where he found it. Why?
- 你好啊 琼斯  - 你好  麦克
- Hello, Jonesey.    - Hello, Mac.
琼斯  你能坐在这儿真惬意
You're lucky I turned up, Jonesey.
外面的歌舞让我头都快炸了
Dovchenko there wanted to blow your brains out.
今天都三次了
That's the third time  I've saved your life.
松开手拷  我好给你个大拥抱
Unshackle me.  I'll give you a big hug.
你当时有手枪啊  为什么束手就擒啊？
You had a Luger pointed at the base of your skull the first time we met.
一切都在我控制之下
I had the situation under control.
- 你欠我的情  - 那你欠他们什么？
- You owe me.    - What do you owe them?
二战结束后你就叛变了
After the war, when you turned,
你给了苏军多少名单？
how many names did you give the Reds?
又有多少人因为你命丧黄泉
You're not looking at the big picture here. How many good men died because of you?
这帮共军终究会放开我的
Eventually, they're gonna let me out of this chair, comrade,
到时看我怎么打断你鼻子吧
and when they do, I'm going to break your nose.
共军？你以为这是因为意识形态？
"Comrade"? You think this is about flags?
为了地图上的线？
About uniforms? You think  this is about lines on a map?
还是为了钱  是吧
It's just about money, isn't it?
我要的才不是钱呢
No. Not only money.
而是堆积如山的钱
A gigantic pile of money.
想想埃克托藏着的宝物
Don't worry about what the Russians will pay.
我才看不上苏军付我的小钱
It's nothing compared to what's at Akator.
一座黄金城  那才是我们的梦想
An entire city of gold. It's what the conquistadors were after.
天啊  琼斯  我们快发财了 比谁都有钱
For God's sake, Jonesey, we'd be rich! Richer than Howard Hughes!
每一分钱上都沾满了鲜血
Blood money, every nickel.
他们不会就此放过你的  哥们
I need you to see  the angle here, mate.
放聪明点  做该做的事…
Be smart. Do the right thing. Just like in ...
还记得在柏林吗？懂我的意思没？
Like in Berlin. Got me?
就和在柏林一样
Just like in Berlin.
你要我出去是吧  去看歌舞
You want me to trot off, or should we sing a song?
幸好当初没杀你  琼斯博士
How fortunate our failure  to kill you, Dr. Jones.
你又为我们服务了一次
You survive to be of service to us once again.
你了解我的  总是助人为乐
Well, you know me,  always glad to help.
掌控死亡的力量才会摧毁这世界
"Now I am become death, the destroyer of worlds."
你记得这些话吗？
You recognize those words?
出自你们的奥本海默博士  在他制造了原子弹之后
It was your own Dr. Oppenheimer after he created the atomic bomb.
他只是在引用印度教的圣经
He was quoting the Hindu bible.
很明显是威胁
It was nuclear intimidation.
但现在我们唾手可得更高级的武器
But now this next level of weapon is ours to have,
该轮到你们恐惧了
yours to fear.
武器？什么样的武器？
Weapon? What weapon?
精神控制武器
A mind weapon.
心理战的阵地  斯大林的梦想
A new frontier of psychic warfare. That was Stalin's dream.
现在我可明白奥力克斯为何要把骷髅放回原处了
Now I know why Oxley put the  skull back where he found it.
他知道你们在找
He knew you were looking for it.
想必你一见骷髅就知道
That skull is no mere deity carving.
那简直巧夺天工
Surely you knew that the moment you laid eyes on it.
绝非出自人手
It was not made by human hands.
那是谁做的？
Who made it, then?
不是吧
Come on.
我们在新墨西哥州找到的尸骸不是第一具
The body we found in New Mexico was not the first.
在苏联的几处地方也有相同发现
We'd already dissected two others from similar crash sites in Soviet Union.
火星来客
Saucer men from Mars.
关于埃克托的古老传说
The legends about Akator  are all true.
古人是想象不出来的  更不要说建造出来
Early men could not have  conceived it, much less built it.
那是一座高等生物的城池
It was a city of supreme beings ...
他们技术发达  拥有超常能力
with technologies and paranormal abilities.
你这玩笑可开大了
You got to be kidding me.
你自己看吧  信不信由你
Why do you choose not to believe your own eyes?
新墨西哥州找到的样本  让我们充满希望
The New Mexico specimen gave us hope.
当然还有其它样本  骸骨都是由纯水晶制成
Unlike the others we'd found, its skeleton was pure crystal.
能一同找到埃克托  也许我们要到的是同样的东西
A distant cousin, perhaps. Maybe they, too, were sent to find Akator.
也许我们殊途同归
Perhaps we're all searching for the same thing.
- 没有别的解释了  - 总会有其它解释的
- There is no other explanation.    - There's always another explanation.
头骨是公元15世纪从埃克托偷来的
The skull was stolen from Akator in the 15th century.
不论是谁…
Whoever returns it ...
将其归还就能拥有无上的控制力
Returns it to the city temple will gain control over its powers.
我听过这故事
I've heard that bedtime story before.
只是传说  你凭什么认为埃克托真正存在？
It's a legend. Why do you think Akator even existed?
你最好拿这问题问问你的朋友
You should ask your friend that question.
把教授带过来
他肯定去过那儿
We're certain he's been there.
奥克斯利？
Oxley?
是我  印第啊
Ox, it's me, Indy.
奥克斯
Ox?
你是在装疯吧
Ox, you're faking it, right?
透过泪朦朦的双眼我看到…
"Through eyes  that last I saw in tears ..."
奥克斯  听我说  你是哈洛德·奥克斯
Ox, listen to me, pal. Your name is Harold Oxley.
出生于英国利兹
You were born in Leeds, England.
咱俩在芝加哥大学是同窗好友
You and I went to school together at the University of Chicago.
你从来不曾像今天这样好笑  我叫…
And you were never this interesting. My name is ...
我叫小亨利·琼斯
My name is Henry Jones, Jr.
你们把他怎么了？
What have you done to him?
什么都没做  都怪那该死的颅骨
We ain't done a thing. It's the bloody skull.
博士会带我们去埃克托
He is the divining rod that will lead us to Akator.
但我们需要个翻译
But we need someone to interpret him for us.
因为他精神状态看来不佳  希望你的精神状态比他好些
His mind, it seems, is quite weak. Let's hope yours is stronger.
水晶骷髅可以刺激大脑中尚不为人知的部分
The skull's crystal stimulates an undeveloped part of the human brain,
打开心灵通道
opening a psychic channel.
奥克斯就是因为盯着它太久 才丧失了心智
Oxley lost control of his mind by staring too long into its eyes.
我们坚信  你也这么做就能和他沟通了
We believe you can get through to  him after you have done the same.
还有个更好的办法  不如你来试试看
I've got a better idea.  You look at it.
似乎骷髅头不是同每个人都有交流
The skull does not speak  to everyone, it seems.
你想必不害怕吧 琼斯博士
Surely you're not afraid,  Dr. Jones.
你穷尽一生追寻的答案
You've spent your entire life searching for answers.
想想这双眼之后的真相吧
Think of the truth behind those eyes.
可能世上还有数百个这样的骷髅头
There may be hundreds of skulls at Akator.
谁找到他们  谁就能掌握有史以来最强大的力量
Whoever finds them will control  the greatest natural force the world has ever known.
人类心智的力量
Power over the mind of man.
小心哦  你可能真的会如愿以偿
Be careful, you might get  exactly what you wish for.
我通常都心想事成
I usually do.
想象一下
Imagine.
透过层层防线探知敌军秘密
To peer across the world and know the enemy's secrets.
把我们的思想灌输给你们的领袖
To place our thoughts into the minds of your leaders.
让老师教授真正的历史
Make your teachers teach the true version of history,
让你们的战士听从我方指挥
your soldiers attack on our command.
你可以神游世界  强大无比
We'll be everywhere at once, more powerful than a whisper,
在睡梦中即可改变世界
invading your dreams, thinking your thoughts for you while you sleep.
这会改变你的 琼斯博士
We will change you, Dr. Jones,
你们所有人都会由内到外改变
all of you, from the inside.
你将会变成我们的一员
We will turn you into us.
而最好的一点  你察觉不到这种转变
And the best part? You won't even know it's happening.
回归
Return.
Return?
够了
That's enough.
够了 如果他死了 我们到不了那儿
That's enough. If he dies, we can't get there.
盖起来
Cover it.
亨利
Henry.
醒醒 琼斯
You all right, Jonesey?
- 你把我的鼻子打断了  - 告诉过你
- You broke my nose!    - I told you.
够了 你去和奥克斯谈话  然后带领我们去埃克托
Enough! You will speak to Oxley and lead us to Akator, yes?
做梦
把他带出去
Take him outside.
- 孩子 你还好吗？ - 这是我最糟的一学期了
- You all right, kid?    - They left my bike at the cemetery.
- 你还好吧？ - 他们没把我的摩托车带来
- Yeah, but you're all right?    - They left my bike.
慢着  慢着  慢着
Whoa! Whoa, whoa. Wait, wait, wait. Stop, stop, stop.
我准备好了  什么都别给这些猪
I'm ready.  Don't give these pigs a thing.
你听见他说什么了
You heard him.
很明显 我还不想让他死呢
Clearly I have chosen the wrong pressure point.
也许我可以找到个更敏感脆弱的
Perhaps I can find a more sensitive one.
把她带出来!
把手拿开  你们这些狗杂种
Get your hands off me, you rotten Russki son of a bitch!
印第安纳·琼斯
Indiana Jones.
你总是个扫把星
About time you showed up.
- 妈  - 甜心
- Mom!    - Sweetheart.
"妈妈"？
"Mom"?
你在这儿干嘛
What are you doing here?
别说我了  你没受伤吧？
Forget about me. Are you all right?
- "妈妈"？ - 年轻人  我明明告诉过你...
- "Mom"?  - Young man, I specifically told you ...
- 不要来这  - 玛丽安是你妈妈？
- not to come here.    - Marion is your mother?
你信里可没讲  电话里也没讲
You never wrote that. You never  said that in any phone calls.
玛丽安·瑞文伍德是你妈？
Marion Ravenwood is your mother?
天啊 印第  生个儿子没那么难
For God's sake, Indy,  it's not that hard.
我知道 我的意思是  我从来没认为你…
No, I mean, I just never thought ...
在你离开之后还活得挺好
I would have a life after you left.
- 这可不是我的意思  - 生活得很滋润
- That's not what I meant.    - A damn good life!
- 那就好  - 生活得好的不能再好了
- Well, that's fine.    - A damn good, really good life!
- 我也是  - 真的吗？
- Well, so have I!    - Yeah?
你是生活在人类遗址里
You still leaving a trail of human wreckage,
还是退休了？
or have you retired?
为什么这样问？想约我吗？
Why? You looking for a date?
约谁都不约你
With anybody but you.
好啦 琼斯博士  你会帮我们吗？
So, Dr. Jones, you will help us?
说行就可以了
A simple "yes" will do.
玛丽安  你为什么跑去让人家绑架
Oh, Marion, you had to go and get yourself kidnapped.
你也没做什么好事
Not like you did any better.
还是老样子
Same old, same old.
小亨利·琼斯
Henry Jones, Jr.
- 小亨利·琼斯  - 没错  是我 听我说
- Henry Jones, Jr. ...    - That's right, Ox. Listen to me.
双手放在金钥匙上
"To lay their just hands on that Golden Key ...
- 打开永恒之殿的大门  - 什么宫殿…
- "that ope's the Palace of Eternity."    - Palace of ...
他说过这句话  什么意思？
It's from Milton. He's said it before. Why?
奥克斯  你得告诉我们怎么去埃克托
Ox, you got to tell us how to get to Akator ...
不然他们会杀了玛丽安的
or they're gonna kill Marion.
透过泪朦朦的双眼看见金色图像重现…
"Through eyes that last I saw in tears, here in death's dream kingdom ..."
哈洛德  他们会杀掉安不勒的小女儿
Harold, they're gonna kill Abner's little girl.
告诉我们怎么去那儿  我需要详细…
You got to tell us how to get there. We need ...
给我张纸  随便什么能写字的东西
Get me paper.  Something to write with.
快拿张纸来!
让他画下来  早该料到这一点的
Autowriting!  I should have seen this.
- 小亨利·琼斯  - 没错  奥克斯
- Henry Jones, Jr.    - Right. That's right, Ox.
往下落三次
Three times it drops.  The way down.
- 3次…  - 象形文字记载？
- Three times ...    - Pictographs.
象形文字
Ideograms.
很好  奥克斯  很好
Good, Ox. Good.
奥克斯
Ox?
是我啊  奥克斯
It's me, Ox.
我是马特  看着我  看着我  是我
It's Mutt, Ox. Hey, look at me. Look at me. It's me.
是我啊
It's me.
弯曲的线条绝对代表河水  紧闭的双眼代表睡觉
The wavy lines mean water, of course. Closed eyes mean sleep.
空中闪烁的太阳表示时刻  时期
The sun with the arc over the sky stands for time, duration.
"现在"这个词表示"直到"
The word "now" is "until."
紧挨的两条蛇
These two close together,
昂起身子是一个神
the horizon and the snake, mean one thought.
地平线代表世界
The horizon stood for the world,
这个代表"巨大的"
but it didn't mean the Earth. It meant big, great.
长眠于巨蛇下的大河
"The water sleeps until the great snake."
这不仅仅是图画  而是方位  给我张地图
These aren't just drawings, they're directions. Get me a map!
地图!
大蛇是亚马孙河
The great snake is the Amazon, of course,
睡觉？哪条河会睡觉？
but "sleep," what water sleeps?
这儿 索拿河  葡萄牙语里是"睡眠"的意思
Here! Sono. The Portuguese word for "sleep."
没错  的确是这样
Yes, good. Exactly.
色法罗河在此处转弯  与索拿河交汇
He wants us to follow this curve of the Sono ...
在东南方与亚马逊交汇
down to where it meets the Amazon to the southeast.
其余的我就不确定了
After that, I'm not sure.
王国  梦境  眼泪  双眼… 不知到底什么意思
Kingdom of dreams, tears and eyes ... I have no idea what he means.
但也可能指的是路线
This could be the route, though.
那儿人烟罕至  属于卡锐兵平原
It's a completely unexplored part of the canopy.
快跑  快  快  快  快
Go, go, go, go, go! Come on!
- 我们到底在干嘛  小子？ - 他们会杀死我们的
- Kid, what the hell are we doing, kid?    - They were going to kill us!
- 也许吧  - 得有人采取措施
- Well, maybe.    - Somebody had to do something!
- 其它的措施还好些  - 至少我有个计划
- Something else would have been good.    - At least I got a plan.
不可理喻  哈洛德  跟上
This is intolerable. Harold, for God's sake, keep up.
妈？
Mom?
- 别过来  - 停下  别动
- Stay back!    - Stop! Stop! Stop! Don't move.
乱动会形成空间  导致下沉
Moving makes space, space will make you sink.
我可以把腿拔出来…
No, I think I can get out  if I can just ...
别动 往外拔只会更糟
Stop it! You're pulling against a vacuum.
先冷静下来
It's like trying to lift a car. Just stay calm.
好  我不慌
Okay, I'm calm.
- 怎么了？流沙？ - 我冷静
- What is it? Quicksand?    - I'm calm.
- 不对  是干沙  - 我在下沉  但我冷静
- No, it's a dry sand pit.    - I'm sinking, but I'm calm.
流沙混合了沙  水和泥
Quicksand is a mix of sand, mud and water.
基于粘性  它并不像人们想得那么危险
And depending on the viscosity, it's not as dangerous as people sometimes think.
看在老天的份上  琼斯
For Pete's sake, Jones,
这可不是在学校
we're not in school!
别担心  没什么好担心的  除非…
Don't worry. There's nothing to worry about unless there's a ...
这样才麻烦
A void collapse.
我去拿东西救你们出来
I'll go get something  to pull you out.
奥克斯 别傻站着
Ox, don't just sit there.
看在上帝的面上 老兄 找人来帮忙
For God's sake, man, go get help!
- 救命  - 帮忙
- Help?    - Help!
救命
Help?
去找人帮忙  去呀
Help! Go!
马特可能有些冲动
Mutt can be a little impetuous.
那不算是世上最坏的性质
It's not the worst quality  in the world.
双手上举  那小子回来的时候  抓住递来的东西
Keep your arms above the surface. When the kid comes back, grab on.
- 印第  他是…  - 他是个好孩子  玛丽
- Indy, he ...    - He's a good kid, Marion.
别再拿学习唠叨他
You should get off his back about school.
- 马特  我是说…  - 他救了大伙
- Mutt, I mean ...    - Not everybody's cut out for it.
他名叫亨利
His name is Henry!
亨利  好名字
Henry. Good name.
他是你的儿子
He's your son.
我儿子？
My son?
亨利·琼斯  三世
Henry Jones the Third.
你为什么没逼他完成学业？
Why the hell didn't you  make him finish school?
妈 抓好了
Mom, grab on! Grab it!
我抓稳了
I got it.
加油啊 老妈 拉  使劲儿拉
Come on, Mom!  Pull, pull, pull, pull!
拉啊
Pull!
抓着呀
Grab on.
- 抓住  - 抓住那蛇  印第
- Grab it.    - Just grab it, Indy.
它只吃老鼠
It's a rat snake!
- 吃老鼠的蛇没这么大  - 这只就这么大
- Rat snakes aren't that big.    - Well, this one is, all right?
没毒的  抓住
It's not even poisonous.  Now grab on!
- 去拿别的东西  - 拿什么？
- Go get something else.    - Like what?
绳子之类
Like a rope or something.
这儿可找不到绳子  抓住蛇
There's no Sears and Roebuck here! Grab the snake!
- 也许我就能触到底了  - 不会到底的  抓着
- Maybe I can touch the bottom.    - There's no bottom. Now grab it.
我脚尖已触到底了
No, I think  I can feel it with my feet.
- 抓着蛇  - 别那样喊它
- Grab the snake!    - Stop calling it that!
这就是条蛇  要我怎么叫？
It's a snake! What do you want me to call it?
- 叫"绳子"  - 什么？
- Say "rope."    - What?
说"抓住绳子"
Say "grab the rope."
- 抓着绳子  - 抓着绳子
- Grab the rope!    - Grab the rope!
抓紧了
Hold tight. It's slimy.
扯啊
Pull!
儿子 把它扔远点好吗？
Get rid of that thing, will you, Son?
你怕蛇
Afraid of snakes.
你真是个疯老头
You are one crazy old man.
你下一步准备干什么啊  琼斯？
Why do you have to do everything the hard way, Jonesey?
干得漂亮啊  奥克斯  谢谢啊
Good work, Ox. Thanks.
找人帮忙
Help.
不可能  他是英国人  我老爸是皇家空军飞行员
No. No, he was British. My dad was an RAF pilot.
是战斗英雄  不是什么大学老师
He was a war hero, not some schoolteacher!
不是  甜心  柯林是你的继父
No, sweetheart. Colin was your stepfather.
你3个月大时  我才和他约会
We started dating when you were three months old.
他是个好人
He was a good man.
等等 柯林？是那个柯林·威廉姆斯吗？
Wait, wait, wait. Colin? As in Colin Williams? You ...
你和他结婚了？是我介绍你们认识的
You married him? I introduced you!
你管我最后嫁给谁呢!
I think you gave up your vote on who I married ...
婚礼前一周你和我分手
when you decided to break it off a week before the wedding!
我俩都清楚  咱们的婚姻不会幸福的
I think we both knew, Marion, it wasn't going to work.
你才不知道呢  不然怎么没跟我说过
You didn't know that. Why didn't  you ever talk to me about it?
因为每一次吵架都是你赢
Because we never had an argument I won!
你回不上嘴可不是我的错
It's not my fault  if you can't keep up!
我不想伤了你的心
I didn't want to hurt you!
老天慈悲  闭嘴吧
For love of God, shut the hell up!
你就从来没觉得奇怪为何几年前奥克斯不理你了
Didn't you ever wonder years ago why Ox stopped talking to you?
他恨你离我而去
He hated that you ran away.
你们两个别吵了
Would you two just stop?
没错  玛丽安  别让小孩子看见爹妈吵架
Yeah, Marion, let's not let  the kid see mom and dad fight.
- 你不是我爹  明白吗？ - 我是你爹
- You're not my dad, okay?    - You bet I am.
我还告诉你
And I got news for you.
你得回学校完成学业
You're gonna go back  and finish school.
真的？
Really? What happened to,
你不记得说过
"There's not a damn thing wrong with it, kid,
"做自己喜欢的事"之类的话了吗？
"and don't let anybody else tell you any different"? You don't remember saying that?
那是在我知道你是我儿子之前
That was before I was your father!
- 你才不是我爹!  - 没错  他是你爹
- You're not my father!    - Oh, yes, he is your father.
你应该把孩子的事告诉我  玛丽安
You should have told me about the kid, Marion.
我有权知道
I had a right to know.
分手后你无影无踪了
You vanished after that.
- 我有写信啊  - 一年之后
- I wrote.    - A year later!
收到信时  马特已经出生  我也结婚了
By then, Mutt was born and I was married!
那你何必现在费事告诉我？
Why are you bothering  to tell me now?
因为我认为我们快死了
Because I thought we were gonna die!
死不了
Not yet!
拿到了吗？
Got it?
噢 糟了
Oh, shit.
我敢肯定我不是你的唯一
I'm sure I wasn't the only one to go on with my life.
这么多年来你一定有不少红颜知己吧
There must've been plenty of  women for you over the years.
是有几个  但是全有一样的毛病
Yeah. There were a few, but they all had the same problem.
什么毛病？
Yeah? What's that?
她们不是你  亲爱的
They weren't you, honey.
我们要抢在他们之前找到骷髅
We got to get Oxley back, get our hands on that skull ...
然后送到埃克托  抓住方向盘
and get to Akator before they do. Grab the wheel.
他打算怎么做？
What's he gonna do now?
- 我不觉得他有那么长远的计划  - 对
- I don't think he plans that far ahead.    - Yeah.
- 往右边挪挪好吗  儿子？ - 别叫我"儿子"
- Scooch over, will you, Son?    - Don't call me "son." Don't.
如果是我  就堵住耳朵
I think I'd cover my ears  if I were you.
低头  低头
Duck! Duck!
快 快
Move, move!
在那个博士身边停下
Pull up next to that duck.
小亨利·琼斯
Henry Jones, Jr.
快走!
把这个带走
琼斯!
Jones!
拦住他!
快 快 来这辆车
Come on! Come on!
卧倒
Get down!
奥克斯拿着骷髅呢  玛丽安握好方向盘
Ox has got the skull. Marion, take the wheel.
你又让她开车？
That's not fair.  She drove the truck.
别孩子气  找武器和他们打
Don't be a child. Find something to fight with.
琼斯
Jonesey!
- 琼斯  - 你好啊 麦克
- Jonesey!    - Hi, Mac.
- 印第 印第  - 闭嘴  闭嘴
- Indy. Indy! Indy!    - Shut up! Shut up!
- 你这愚蠢的狗杂种  我是中情局的  - 中情局
- You stupid son of a bitch! I'm CIA.    - CIA.
我不想要你死  就像在柏林时一样
I almost screamed it at you in the tent. I said, "Just like Berlin."
我们在柏林干嘛  兄弟？
What were we in Berlin, mate?
- 双面间谍  - 把骷髅头扔给我
- Double agents!    - The skull!
抓住那包袱
Throw me the skull!
注意姿势
Riposte.
双脚别站那么开  注意姿势
Get on your front foot. Riposte.
又不是比赛  老妈
It's not a match, Mom.
你打架就是个新手  打得快 输得也快
You fight like a young man, eager to begin, quick to finish.
马特  别和她纠缠了
Mutt, disengage!
我拿到骷髅了
Hey! Hey, I got the skull!
- 扔过来  - 扔过来
- Throw the bag! Throw it!    - Throw the bag!
- 枪  - 小心枪
- Gun!    - Gun!
看什么看  她就要逃走了
What are you looking at, Daddy-o? She's getting away!
到那边去
这太危险了
This is very dangerous.
再见了  琼斯博士
Do svidanya, Dr. Jones.
琼斯
Jones!
拐弯
Turn!
- 食人蚁  - 什么？
- Siafu.    - What?
吃人的蚂蚁 快走
Big damn ants! Go!
去河边
Run to the river!
抓住他们
带着骷髅往河边跑
Get to the river!
上车  快快
Jump in! Come on! Come on!
妈  那儿有悬崖
Mom, there's a cliff!
- 琼斯  快来!  - 琼斯 上车
- Jonesey, come on!    - Get in, Jones!
- 妈 停下  - 快减速
- Mom, stop.    - Mom, slow down.
- 停下 亲爱的  - 快减速
- Honey, stop.    - Slow down, Mom.
- 你要开下悬崖了  - 我自有办法
- You're gonna go off the cliff.    - That's the idea.
- 但不是什么好办法  我来  - 相信我
- Bad idea. Give me the wheel.    - Trust me!
开慢点
Slow down!
- 再也不要那么干了  - 好的 亲爱的
- Don't ever do that again.    - Yes, dear.
往下落三次
Three times it drops.
倒车  转过来
Reverse. Put it in reverse!  Full reverse!
我在尝试
I'm trying! I'm trying!
下去的路
The way down.
陆地上的那条道  你是说从陆地上走
He means by land.  He came by land.
- 往下落三次？ - 往下落三次
- Three times it drops?    - Three times it drops.
你说什么啊？
What is he talking about?
他的意思是第一次
He means one!
那是第二次
Two!
第三次
Three.
你没事吧？松手
You okay? Babe? Let go.
透过泪朦朦的双眼
"Through eyes that last I saw in tears."
看见金色图像重现
"The golden vision reappears!"
金子 告诉我
Gold. I'm in.
透过双眼…泪朦朦的双眼  我们得穿过瀑布
Through eyes ... Through eyes in tears. We got to go through that waterfall!
必须归还骷髅  我去吧  其它人不必来
The skull has to be returned. I'll do it. Nobody else has to come.
谁在乎？
Who cares?
它只能给我们带来麻烦
It's brought us nothing but trouble.
看把他变成什么样了
Look what it did to him.
- 我必须得去归还  - 为什么是你去？
- I have to return it.    - Why you?
因为它告诉我要去
Because it told me to.
- 欧克斯人  他们的图腾  壁画  - 欧克斯  别走
- Ochre, iron oxide, charcoal.    - Oxy, stay with us.
这有多久的历史了？
How old is this?
四五千年前的文明  与金字塔一样古老
Four or five thousand years. Old as the pyramids.
崇拜太阳神的人  和埃及人一样
Look, sun worshippers, like the Egyptians.
这是新鲜的  刚刚有人用过
This is fresh.  These were just used.
更多的崇拜者
More worshippers.
没错  但他们不崇拜太阳
Yeah, but that's not the sun they're worshipping.
有人来过
Someone came ...
农耕
and taught the Ugha farming.
灌溉
Irrigation.
奥克斯  怎么啦？
Ox, what is it?
我明白你的意思  奥克斯
I think I understand, Ox.
有人来过？
Someone came?
那骷髅头和壁画中的一模一样
Are they the same?
不止一个  看
There were more. Look.
一共有十三个  围成一圈
Thirteen in a circle.
路在哪儿  奥克斯
Show us the way, Ox.
- 我们走  快  快  - 快跑
- Let's go. Go, go, go! Run! Run, go!    - Go!
印第
Indy!
小琼
Jonesey!
奥克斯
Oxley!
你到过这里  怎么逃脱的？
You were here before. How did you get past them?
起来  麦克  起来  麦克
Come on, Mac. Come on! Come on, Mac.
快来  来  来  奥克斯
Come on, come on, come on.
双手放在金钥匙上
"To lay their just hands on that Golden Key ...
- 打开永恒宫殿的大门  - 来吧  奥克斯
- "that ope's the Palace of Eternity."    - Come on, Ox.
好样儿的  你是好样儿的
You did good, Ox. You did good.
黄金之城  那黄金在哪儿？
City of gold.  So where's all the gold?
看这地方有多老了
Look at the state of this place.
蠢透了  真是浪费我的时间
What a stupid legend. What a waste of my time.
奥克斯从前来过这里  但他没法子进入神殿
Ox was here before, but he  couldn't get into the temple,
所以他就又把骷髅送了回去
so he took the skull back to the cemetery, where he found it.
你的双手放在纯金钥匙上
"To lay their just hands on that Golden Key ...
用来打开永恒宫殿的大门
"that ope's the Palace of Eternity."
宫殿金钥匙？
Key that ope's the palace.
石碑! 这石碑就是钥匙？
The obelisk.  The obelisk is the key?
奥克斯  你找什么？
What are you looking for, Ox?
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
你在监牢里才想明白  对吧
You figured this out in your cell, didn't you, Professor?
让我试一下
Excuse me, Professor.
好极了
Well done.
去搬你自己的石块
Go get your own.
你们听!
Listen.
听见了吗？
Hear that?
闪开  奥克斯  快走!
Get up! Move! Ox, move!
再快点!
Faster! Faster!
Faster!
情况不妙  快
This is not good. Move, Ox! Move!
快点  快点
Quick! Quick! Quick!
我讨厌这样  我讨厌这样
I don't like this!  I don't like it!
- 妈 快点  - 琼斯
- Mom, come on!    - Jonesey!
搞丢了  他把骷髅搞丢了
He dropped it.  He dropped the skull!
还好吗？
Okay?
拿着这个
Hold this.
奥克斯  你没受伤吧？
Ox, you okay?
太好了
Lovely.
好了  咱们走
All right, let's go.
走这边？
This way?
终于看见点值钱的东西了
Now that's more like it.
各个历史时期的文物
There are artifacts from every era of early history.
马其顿文明
Macedonian.
- 苏美尔文明  - 这简直就是天然的收藏展览
- Sumerian.    - This place is the mother lode.
巴比伦文明
Etruscan. Babylonian.
世界上的每个博物馆都会爱死这地方的
There isn't a museum in the world that  wouldn't sell its soul for this lot.
早期的埃及文明
Early Egyptian.
许多许多博物馆  成千上百个  琼斯
Dozens of museums. Hundreds of them, Jonesey!
收藏家
Collectors.
他们是考古学家
They were archeologists.
怎么打开它？
How do we open it?
把它还回去  奥克斯  我承诺过了
I'll give it back, Ox. I promise.
不用再永远等待
No more forever waiting.
马上就好
Soon now.
对不起了  琼斯
Sorry, Jonesey.
你到底为谁工作？三重特务？
So what are you, a triple agent?
哪里  说我是双重特务  不过是谎话而已
Nah, I just lied  about being a double.
看看他们
Look at them!
仍然在等待迷失的那个回归
Still waiting for the return of the one who was lost.
虽然作为个体存在
They are a hive mind.
却心灵相通
One being physically separate, but with a collective consciousness.
合而为一力量会更大  远胜于个体
More powerful together than they can ever be apart.
想象一下  他们能够告诉什么
Imagine what they could tell us.
我想不出来
I can't imagine.
建造神殿的人也想不出来
Neither could the humans that built this temple,
更不用说是你了
and neither can you.
相信我吧 琼斯博士  你在这儿会收到一份礼物
Belief, Dr. Jones, is a gift you have yet to receive.
我的同情
My sympathies.
这点我相信  所以才到这地下来了
Oh, I believe, sister. That's why I'm down here.
- 玛雅语  他在说玛雅语  - 他在说什么？
- Mayan. He's speaking Mayan.    - What does he say?
他说  非常感激  他想要…
He says he's grateful  and he wants ...
它
It.
想要给我们一份礼物
It wants to give us a gift.
丰厚的礼物
A big gift.
告诉我你所知道的一切
Tell me everything you know.
我想知道一切  我想知道
I want to know everything. I want to know.
我预感不妙
I've got a bad feeling about this.
印第
Indy?
看他们的眼睛
The eyes.
他们是什么东西？航天员？
What are they? Spacemen?
他们要回自己的空间去了
Interdimensional beings,  in point of fact.
你终于清醒了  奥克斯
Welcome back, Ox.
那是什么东西？
What the hell is that?
通往另一个空间的通道
A portal! A pathway to another dimension!
我们才不要去呢
I don't think we want  to go that way.
我想知道  我想知道
I want to know. I want to know.
告诉我  我准备好了  我想知道
Tell me. I'm ready.  I want to know.
麦克  麦克  快来吧
Mac! Mac! Come on!
麦克
Mac!
别拿了  现在就走
Mac, damn it, now!
我能看见
I can see.
看见了
I can see!
抓住它
Grab it!
往上爬啊  麦克  我一个人拉不动你
Use your legs, Mac.  I can't do it alone.
没事  小琼
Jonesey!
我会没事的
I'm going to be all right.
够了
No more!
盖上它  快盖上!
Cover it. Cover it.
走
Go!
够了
Enough!
快走  快走
Go! Go!
那痕迹像朵花
Like a broom to their footprints.
他们上哪儿去了？太空？
Where did they go? Space?
不是去了太空  而是空间的缝隙
Not into space. Into the space between spaces.
我不明白
I don't understand.
传说中的黄金城在哪儿？
Why this legend of a city of gold?
在古语中黄金这个词可译成"宝藏"
The Ugha word for gold translates as "treasure."
但宝物指的并非是黄金  而是知识
But their treasure wasn't gold. It was knowledge.
知识才是他们的宝物
Knowledge was their treasure.
难道我们就坐在这儿吗？
What? We're just going to sit here?
孩子  雨林的夜晚来的早
Night falls quick in the jungle, kid.
你不想摸黑翻山越岭吧
You don't want to climb down the mountain in the dark.
不？
No?
我能  跟着我走  来吧
I can. Who's coming with me? Come on.
为何不坐一会儿呢 年轻人
Why don't you stick around, Junior?
我不知道  你为什么不走呢  老爸
I don't know. Why didn't you, Dad?
老爸
Dad!
老爸？
Dad?
你爷爷不定在哪儿偷笑呢
Somewhere your grandpa is laughing.
(小亨利·琼斯教授 副院长)
太好了  棒极了  把字写大点儿 再大点
Marvelous! Perfect! Make the  letters bigger, much bigger.
小亨利·琼斯和玛丽安·瑞文伍德
Henry Jones, Jr., and Marion Ravenwood,
你二人愿意在此神圣仪式上宣布今后共结连理
insomuch in that you two have agreed to live together in holy matrimony,
宣誓彼此珍爱
have promised your love for  each other by these vows ...
执对方之手  交换戒指
the joining of your hands and the giving of these rings,
我现在宣布你们结成夫妻
I now declare you to be husband and wife.
奉上帝之意结合  永不分离
Whom God hath put together, let no one tear asunder.
人生有多少时光都在等待中虚度
"How much of human life is lost in waiting!"
祝贺你们
Congratulations.
可以吻新娘子了
You may kiss your bride.
干得不错  亨利
Well done, Henry!
谢了  奥克斯
Thanks, Ox.